<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research Assistant | Reality Bending Lab</title>
    <link>https://realitybending.github.io/tag/research-assistant/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://realitybending.github.io/tag/research-assistant/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Research Assistant</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://realitybending.github.io/media/icon_hu43f9474a7b47cfb59c41895962a4d3bc_15500_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Research Assistant</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/tag/research-assistant/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Assistant in Psychology / Neuroscience</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-calendar  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Flexible

  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-location-pin  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; University of Sussex, Brighton, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/ResearchAssistant_hu047a13864c1c5f4663f4f8c2cbb91c5b_57192_a604be98f8756b4c9ea26f108ada217f.webp 400w,
               /media/ResearchAssistant_hu047a13864c1c5f4663f4f8c2cbb91c5b_57192_6bfdc3da1f65dd7b626fe503d7c155f3.webp 760w,
               /media/ResearchAssistant_hu047a13864c1c5f4663f4f8c2cbb91c5b_57192_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/media/ResearchAssistant_hu047a13864c1c5f4663f4f8c2cbb91c5b_57192_a604be98f8756b4c9ea26f108ada217f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working as a research assistant (RA) is a formidable opportunity to take on before - eventually - signing up for a PhD. It is a flexible and varied position, and a perfect position to develop key research skills like writing, data analysis or neuroimaging; and eventually later pursue a postgraduate program in psychology/neuroscience/neuropsychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Funded RA positions at Sussex can be seen on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sussex.ac.uk/about/jobs/research-assistant-ref-10411&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recruitment page&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sussex-psychology-placement-year&#34;&gt;Sussex Psychology Placement Year&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students at the University of Sussex can also opt for a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sussex.ac.uk/study/undergraduate/courses/psychology-with-a-professional-placement-year-bsc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;placement year&lt;/a&gt; between the second and third year of their studies. All undergraduates within the School are eligible to complete a placement year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it might seem like it would &amp;ldquo;add&amp;rdquo; one year and &lt;em&gt;delay&lt;/em&gt; the end of the studies, the experience that you could gain is quite invaluable. Doing a full-year placement year in a research lab is the best way to take on larger projects and acquire a comprehensive research experience. Beyond providing you with a massive headstart for the final year, it is a great opportunity to learn new skills and meet many researchers, which will help you refine your career trajectory and maximize your chances of &lt;strong&gt;achieving your goals&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/psychology/internal/students/placements&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sussex-junior-research-associate-jra&#34;&gt;Sussex Junior Research Associate (JRA)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sussex also offers short &lt;strong&gt;summer internship&lt;/strong&gt; opportunities for undergrads interested in developing your research skills and experience. You can apply to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/suro/jra&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sussex Junior Research Associate (JRA) program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to become a research associate and undertake an intensive eight-week research project over the summer break. Find out more information on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/suro/applying&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;how to apply here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sosocbio-undergraduate-summer-studentship&#34;&gt;SoSocBio Undergraduate Summer Studentship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undergraduates residing in the UK can apply for a paid 6 weeks (30hr per week) internship between 1 July and 30 September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information &lt;a href=&#34;https://southcoastbiosciencesdtp.ac.uk/undergraduate-summer-studentship-programme/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;volunteer-research-assistant&#34;&gt;Volunteer Research assistant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/intern/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;voluntary internships&lt;/a&gt; page for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t rely on what is written!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask directly &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/people/&#34;&gt;members of team&lt;/a&gt; (current and past) about their experience in the lab!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Projects</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-calendar  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Flexible

  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-location-pin  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; University of Sussex, Brighton, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/projects_hufda7ce26936a468bfdf9c0fd8ba5e4dc_259429_42ac0e54e1451665e51839be9b7fd82d.webp 400w,
               /media/projects_hufda7ce26936a468bfdf9c0fd8ba5e4dc_259429_64d0c70e21d77587e5f1ab3080d2ee2c.webp 760w,
               /media/projects_hufda7ce26936a468bfdf9c0fd8ba5e4dc_259429_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/media/projects_hufda7ce26936a468bfdf9c0fd8ba5e4dc_259429_42ac0e54e1451665e51839be9b7fd82d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;580&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;projects&#34;&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research in the &lt;strong&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/strong&gt; focuses primarily on the physiological and neurocognitive underpinnings of reality perception and aspects of &lt;strong&gt;reality bending&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g., fiction, deception, fake news, illusions, and altered states of consciousness such as through meditation or immersion). Possible projects include (but are not limited to):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-do-we-know-what-is-real-and-what-does-it-change&#34;&gt;How do we know what is real? And what does it change?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real vs. Fake&lt;/strong&gt;: This project will typically involve presenting some real vs. &amp;ldquo;fake&amp;rdquo; stimuli (e.g., fake news, AI-generated images, &amp;hellip;) to participants and investigate what interindividual/cognitive/emotional factors allows them to discriminate between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotion regulation via fiction&lt;/strong&gt;: believing that something is unreal (regardless of whether it actually is or is not) seem to have some ripple effect on various facets of our body and brain, such as emotions. This project studies the characteristics and potential use of fiction as an emotion regulation strategy. This project can be focused on negative emotions (with threatening/unpleasant stimuli) or &amp;ldquo;positive&amp;rdquo; emotions (e.g., sexual arousal, attractiveness).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authenticity &amp;amp; Neuroaesthetics&lt;/strong&gt;: This project investigates the effect of believing that an artwork is &amp;ldquo;forged&amp;rdquo; (e.g., an imitation of a great painter) on our appraisal of beauty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessment-of---and-relationship-between---bodily-and-cognitive-abilities&#34;&gt;Assessment of - and relationship between - bodily and cognitive abilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neuropsychological assessment of Cognitive Control&lt;/strong&gt;: This project focuses on the development, validation and improvement of a neuropsychological task to reliably measure &amp;ldquo;cognitive control&amp;rdquo; (executive functions). This project requires some interest in neuropsychological assessment, task development and associated technical skills (programming, game development).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physiological Control&lt;/strong&gt;: development of measures (questionnaires, physiological tasks) measuring the ability to voluntarily regulate one&amp;rsquo;s physiology (e.g., heart rate, autonomic reactions, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationship between &lt;strong&gt;Interoception&lt;/strong&gt; and higher-order functions: This project involves measuring various aspects of our relationship with our body (e.g., by measuring cardiac activity) and analyzing its relationship with cognitive abilities (e.g., Self control, emotion regulation) or higher-order constructs (e.g., primal world beliefsLinks to an external site.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secondary &lt;strong&gt;EEG data analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Investigating an existing dataset containing resting state EEG signal, from which one would extract features to try predicting dispositional indices (such as primal world beliefs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;non-invasive-induction-of-altered-states-of-consciousness&#34;&gt;Non-invasive induction of altered states of consciousness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotion regulation via distancing&lt;/strong&gt;: by instructing people to change their state of mind (e.g., &amp;ldquo;see the events in a detached manner, like a fly on the wall&amp;rdquo;), we hope to manipulate aspects of the sense of reality - such as absorption and psychological distance - and compare its effect (in particular on emotions) with that of other emotion regulation strategies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we &lt;strong&gt;manipulate the state of consciousness&lt;/strong&gt; and observe actual effects on the performance at various cognitive tasks? For instance, via hypnosis or mindfulness-like instructions, sound stimulation (binaural beats, drumming, &amp;hellip;), sensory deprivation (&amp;ldquo;floating&amp;rdquo; tanks). We study the role of expectations and try to isolate the mechanism of change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qualitative + quantitative&lt;/strong&gt; project: Investigation into the world of &amp;ldquo;reality shifters&amp;rdquo;, people claiming that have shifted between realities. Understand their language, personality, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;metascience--data-science--software-development&#34;&gt;Metascience / Data science / Software development&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigation of &lt;strong&gt;scientific practices&lt;/strong&gt;: to what extent scientists engage in &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; practices (e.g., open science, slow science, preregistration, registered reports, &amp;hellip;) and what factors (e.g., career level, time, ideology, &amp;hellip;) are driving their adoption (or lack thereof). This might involve things like validating assessment tools (such as questionnaires or gamified measures like quizzes), distributing it widely and analysing the results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving access of &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; to psychologists: R outputs can be complex, and we are developing tools to facilitate its understanding (e.g., the reportLinks to an external site. package). This project involves implementing functions in R to help communicate and interpret statistical results. This project requires some interest in programming and stats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neurophysiological signal analysis in &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;: implementation and validation of new algorithms in Python, related for instance to chaos theory, EEG signal analysis, etc. This project requires some interest in programming, computer science and mathematics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychophysiological methods&lt;/strong&gt;: what is the optimal electrode configuration for recording skin conductance responses (often used as a marker of emotions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Role of beauty in science: Is the impact of research publications related to the aeshetic qualities of figures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other--collaborations&#34;&gt;Other / Collaborations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://canvas.sussex.ac.uk/courses/30420/pages/theodoros-karapanagiotidis-2-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Theodoros Karapanagiotidis&lt;/a&gt;: project involving secondary behavioural data analysis, exploring questions about the nature of thoughts, their patterns, the impact of mood and ongoing experience , and how they vary in in real-life settings. By analysing existing data, students will be able to examine the links between ongoing thoughts, brain structure and function, and their potential implications for mental health and well-being.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these projects share strong links with philosophical concepts (e.g., the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paradox_of_fiction&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paradox of fiction&lt;/a&gt;) and/or carry some clinical relevance (e.g., for the understanding and treatment of mood/psychotic/dissociative disorders). Also, note that the lab is radically engaged in open science and, ultimately, quantitative methodologies: thus, &lt;strong&gt;most projects would typically require a substantial use of R&lt;/strong&gt; (or Python) at some stage. However, it&amp;rsquo;s totally okay not to feel proficient at these skills at the start, but the important thing is to be interested and motivated to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects might be conducted individually, in pairs, or in a group, depending on needs. Attending weekly lab meetings is also expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills&#34;&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joining the &lt;strong&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/strong&gt; will help you develop unique skills that your might not find in other labs, that will give an edge to your profile for future applications. These include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neuroimaging (EEG)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psychophysiology (multimodal bodily recordings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational Bayesian modelling with R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced programming with Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open science best practices (using GitHub and various cutting edge tools)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t rely on what is written!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask directly &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/people/&#34;&gt;members of team&lt;/a&gt; (current and past) about their experience in the lab!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
