<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Internship | Reality Bending Lab</title>
    <link>https://realitybending.github.io/tag/internship/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://realitybending.github.io/tag/internship/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Internship</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://realitybending.github.io/media/icon_hu11326173534259092558.png</url>
      <title>Internship</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/tag/internship/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Assistant in Psychology / Neuroscience</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-calendar  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Flexible

  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-location-pin  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; University of Sussex, Brighton, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/ResearchAssistant_hu15398285732575958578.webp 400w,
               /media/ResearchAssistant_hu3678279592926979815.webp 760w,
               /media/ResearchAssistant_hu9270665831741361063.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/media/ResearchAssistant_hu15398285732575958578.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working as a research assistant (RA) is a formidable opportunity to take on before - eventually - signing up for a PhD. It is a flexible and varied position, and a perfect position to develop key research skills like writing, data analysis or neuroimaging; and eventually later pursue a postgraduate program in psychology/neuroscience/neuropsychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Funded RA positions at Sussex can be seen on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sussex.ac.uk/about/jobs/research-assistant-ref-10411&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;recruitment page&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sussex-psychology-placement-year&#34;&gt;Sussex Psychology Placement Year&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students at the University of Sussex can also opt for a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sussex.ac.uk/study/undergraduate/courses/psychology-with-a-professional-placement-year-bsc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;placement year&lt;/a&gt; between the second and third year of their studies. All undergraduates within the School are eligible to complete a placement year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it might seem like it would &amp;ldquo;add&amp;rdquo; one year and &lt;em&gt;delay&lt;/em&gt; the end of the studies, the experience that you could gain is quite invaluable. Doing a full-year placement year in a research lab is the best way to take on larger projects and acquire a comprehensive research experience. Beyond providing you with a massive headstart for the final year, it is a great opportunity to learn new skills and meet many researchers, which will help you refine your career trajectory and maximize your chances of &lt;strong&gt;achieving your goals&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/psychology/internal/students/placements&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sussex-junior-research-associate-jra&#34;&gt;Sussex Junior Research Associate (JRA)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sussex also offers short &lt;strong&gt;summer internship&lt;/strong&gt; opportunities for undergrads interested in developing your research skills and experience. You can apply to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/suro/jra&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sussex Junior Research Associate (JRA) program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to become a research associate and undertake an intensive eight-week research project over the summer break. Find out more information on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/suro/applying&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;how to apply here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See this &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/post/2024-03-12-jingjra/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;blogpost&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for a testimony.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sosocbio-undergraduate-summer-studentship&#34;&gt;SoSocBio Undergraduate Summer Studentship&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undergraduates residing in the UK can apply for a paid 6 weeks (30hr per week) internship between 1 July and 30 September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information &lt;a href=&#34;https://southcoastbiosciencesdtp.ac.uk/undergraduate-summer-studentship-programme/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-bursaries&#34;&gt;Other Bursaries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.the-bns.org/grants&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neuropsychology International Fellowship (NIF)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Small bursaries from the British Neuropsychological Society to support small research internship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;volunteer-research-assistant&#34;&gt;Volunteer Research assistant&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/intern/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;voluntary internships&lt;/a&gt; page for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t rely on what is written!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask directly &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/people/&#34;&gt;members of team&lt;/a&gt; (current and past) about their experience in the lab!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internship in Psychology / Neuroscience</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/intern/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/intern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-calendar  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Flexible

  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-location-pin  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; University of Sussex, Brighton, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/internship_hu13826774581098111831.webp 400w,
               /media/internship_hu9360437051267310207.webp 760w,
               /media/internship_hu859512708784583094.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/media/internship_hu13826774581098111831.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a undergrad student, doing a &lt;strong&gt;voluntary internship&lt;/strong&gt; can be a good idea to get some first exposure with research, develop some useful skills and start growing your professional network. &lt;strong&gt;This is not by any means a necessity or a requirement&lt;/strong&gt;, so don&amp;rsquo;t worry &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; if you cannot afford (financially or in term of availabilities) to volunteer, and check-out instead possibly &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;funded&lt;/a&gt; positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sussex Psychology Placement Year&lt;/strong&gt;: Check-out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Research Assistant&lt;/a&gt; page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sussex Junior Research Assistant (JRA)&lt;/strong&gt;: Check-out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Research Assistant&lt;/a&gt; page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SoSocBio Undergraduate Summer Studentship&lt;/strong&gt;: Check-out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/assistant/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Research Assistant&lt;/a&gt; page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact.&lt;/strong&gt; Send CV to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:D.Makowski@sussex.ac.uk&#34;&gt;D.Makowski@sussex.ac.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;em&gt;explicitly&lt;/em&gt; say that you are interested in volunteering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t rely on what is written!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask directly &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/people/&#34;&gt;members of team&lt;/a&gt; (current and past) about their experience in the lab!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Projects</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://realitybending.github.io/jobs/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-calendar  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Flexible

  &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-location-pin  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; University of Sussex, Brighton, UK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/research_diagram_hu13304367772662489184.webp 400w,
               /media/research_diagram_hu11165237989395795884.webp 760w,
               /media/research_diagram_hu1536842033761964670.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/media/research_diagram_hu13304367772662489184.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;578&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;projects&#34;&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research in the &lt;strong&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/strong&gt; focuses primarily on the physiological and neurocognitive underpinnings of reality perception and aspects of &lt;strong&gt;reality bending&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g., fiction, deception, fake news, illusions, and altered states of consciousness such as through meditation or immersion). Possible projects include (but are not limited to):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-do-we-know-what-is-real-and-what-does-it-change&#34;&gt;How do we know what is real? And what does it change?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real vs. Fake&lt;/strong&gt;: This project will typically involve presenting some real vs. &amp;ldquo;fake&amp;rdquo; stimuli (e.g., fake news, AI-generated images, &amp;hellip;) to participants and investigate what interindividual/cognitive/emotional factors allows them to discriminate between the two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotion regulation via fiction&lt;/strong&gt;: believing that something is unreal (regardless of whether it actually is or is not) seem to have some ripple effect on various facets of our body and brain, such as emotions. This project studies the characteristics and potential use of fiction as an emotion regulation strategy. This project can be focused on negative emotions (with threatening/unpleasant stimuli) or &amp;ldquo;positive&amp;rdquo; emotions (e.g., sexual arousal, attractiveness).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authenticity &amp;amp; Neuroaesthetics&lt;/strong&gt;: This project investigates the effect of believing that an artwork is &amp;ldquo;forged&amp;rdquo; (e.g., an imitation of a great painter) on our appraisal of beauty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;assessment-of-bodily-and-cognitive-abilities-and-their-relationship&#34;&gt;Assessment of bodily and cognitive abilities and their relationship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neuropsychological assessment of Cognitive Control&lt;/strong&gt;: This project focuses on the development, validation and improvement of a neuropsychological task to reliably measure &amp;ldquo;cognitive control&amp;rdquo; (executive functions). This project requires some interest in neuropsychological assessment, task development and associated technical skills (programming, game development).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physiological Control&lt;/strong&gt;: development of measures (questionnaires, physiological tasks) measuring the ability to voluntarily regulate one&amp;rsquo;s physiology (e.g., heart rate, autonomic reactions, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationship between &lt;strong&gt;Interoception&lt;/strong&gt; and higher-order functions: This project involves measuring various aspects of our relationship with our body (e.g., by measuring cardiac activity) and analyzing its relationship with cognitive abilities (e.g., Self control, emotion regulation) or higher-order constructs (e.g., primal world beliefsLinks to an external site.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secondary &lt;strong&gt;EEG data analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Investigating an existing dataset containing resting state EEG signal, from which one would extract features to try predicting dispositional indices (such as primal world beliefs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;non-invasive-induction-of-altered-states-of-consciousness&#34;&gt;Non-invasive induction of altered states of consciousness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotion regulation via distancing&lt;/strong&gt;: by instructing people to change their state of mind (e.g., &amp;ldquo;see the events in a detached manner, like a fly on the wall&amp;rdquo;), we hope to manipulate aspects of the sense of reality - such as absorption and psychological distance - and compare its effect (in particular on emotions) with that of other emotion regulation strategies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we &lt;strong&gt;manipulate the state of consciousness&lt;/strong&gt; and observe actual effects on the performance at various cognitive tasks? For instance, via hypnosis or mindfulness-like instructions, sound stimulation (binaural beats, drumming, &amp;hellip;), sensory deprivation (&amp;ldquo;floating&amp;rdquo; tanks). We study the role of expectations and try to isolate the mechanism of change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Qualitative + quantitative&lt;/strong&gt; project: Investigation into the world of &amp;ldquo;reality shifters&amp;rdquo;, people claiming that have shifted between realities. Understand their language, personality, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;metascience--data-science--software-development&#34;&gt;Metascience / Data science / Software development&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigation of &lt;strong&gt;scientific practices&lt;/strong&gt;: to what extent scientists engage in &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; practices (e.g., open science, slow science, preregistration, registered reports, &amp;hellip;) and what factors (e.g., career level, time, ideology, &amp;hellip;) are driving their adoption (or lack thereof). This might involve things like validating assessment tools (such as questionnaires or gamified measures like quizzes), distributing it widely and analysing the results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving access of &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; to psychologists: R outputs can be complex, and we are developing tools to facilitate its understanding (e.g., the reportLinks to an external site. package). This project involves implementing functions in R to help communicate and interpret statistical results. This project requires some interest in programming and stats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neurophysiological signal analysis in &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;: implementation and validation of new algorithms in Python, related for instance to chaos theory, EEG signal analysis, etc. This project requires some interest in programming, computer science and mathematics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychophysiological methods&lt;/strong&gt;: what is the optimal electrode configuration for recording skin conductance responses (often used as a marker of emotions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Role of beauty in science: Is the impact of research publications related to the aeshetic qualities of figures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other--collaborations&#34;&gt;Other / Collaborations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;https://canvas.sussex.ac.uk/courses/30420/pages/theodoros-karapanagiotidis-2-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Theodoros Karapanagiotidis&lt;/a&gt;: project involving secondary behavioural data analysis, exploring questions about the nature of thoughts, their patterns, the impact of mood and ongoing experience , and how they vary in in real-life settings. By analysing existing data, students will be able to examine the links between ongoing thoughts, brain structure and function, and their potential implications for mental health and well-being.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these projects share strong links with philosophical concepts (e.g., the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paradox_of_fiction&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;paradox of fiction&lt;/a&gt;) and/or carry some clinical relevance (e.g., for the understanding and treatment of mood/psychotic/dissociative disorders). Also, note that the lab is radically engaged in open science and, ultimately, quantitative methodologies: thus, &lt;strong&gt;most projects would typically require a substantial use of R&lt;/strong&gt; (or Python) at some stage. However, it&amp;rsquo;s totally okay not to feel proficient at these skills at the start, but the important thing is to be interested and motivated to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects might be conducted individually, in pairs, or in a group, depending on needs. Attending weekly lab meetings is also expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills&#34;&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joining the &lt;strong&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/strong&gt; will help you develop unique skills that your might not find in other labs, that will give an edge to your profile for future applications. These include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Neuroimaging (EEG)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Psychophysiology (multimodal bodily recordings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational Bayesian modelling with R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced programming with Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open science best practices (using GitHub and various cutting edge tools)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;advice-for-students&#34;&gt;Advice for Students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;choosing-options&#34;&gt;Choosing Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most psychology programs are proposing some optionality, i.e., some modules that you can pick.
While many of them look interesting, you often have to make hard choices.
Many students pick what looks interesting, from various psychology domains (e.g., a bit of social psychology, a module from cognitive, one from clinical etc.).
They might also believe that picking a variety of options will provide them with a &lt;strong&gt;multidisciplinary profile&lt;/strong&gt;, which might be valued later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is, in principle, true, in practice, &lt;strong&gt;a &amp;ldquo;consistent&amp;rdquo; profile is often much more appealing to recruiters&lt;/strong&gt;. For instance, having a set of clinically-relevant options, or cognitive/neuroscience ones, will give you an edge (and sometimes, even for say a &amp;ldquo;neuroscience&amp;rdquo; opportunity, recruiters would prefer a clearly clinical profile rather than a &amp;ldquo;jack of all trades master of none&amp;rdquo; type of one). &lt;strong&gt;Make your choices wisely, and make them with a plan.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t know&lt;/em&gt; what I want to do later, so I want to keep most doors open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s a common issue. You can still keep doors open while at the same time having a coherent profile. You &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; at least have an idea of what subbranch of psychology you &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; want to do (e.g., social psychology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For psychology students at Sussex, if you would like to work with me, I recommend picking some of the following options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cognitive Neuroscience &lt;em&gt;(must have)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conscious and Unconscious Mental Processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biological Psychology of Mental Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perspectives on Psychology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self Regulation: The Science of Achieving Your Goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attention: Distraction, Daydreaming and Diversity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drugs, Brain and Behaviour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t rely on what is written!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask directly &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/people/&#34;&gt;members of team&lt;/a&gt; (current and past) about their experience in the lab!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Junior Research Assistant (JRA) at Sussex: is it worth it?</title>
      <link>https://realitybending.github.io/post/2024-03-12-jingjra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://realitybending.github.io/post/2024-03-12-jingjra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all, I am &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/authors/jingxiong-xu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jing&lt;/a&gt;, and I thought I would share my experience as a Psychology Junior Research Assistant (JRA) at the University of Sussex, as many students might wonder how it is really like. Obviously, I cannot speak for all the labs, but I hope my experience can give you a general idea of what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked as a JRA during summer 2023 at the Reality Bending Lab (ReBeL). And to put it simply, I think it was &lt;strong&gt;the most valuable experience&lt;/strong&gt; during my undergraduate journey &lt;em&gt;(PS: I have &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; written this at gunpoint)&lt;/em&gt;. During these three months, I was supervised by Dr Makowski to work on a piece of original research, that thought me a lot about programming, cognitive neuropsychology, physio recordings and how real research is done. Additionally, know that it is possible to stay in the same lab next academic year, to do your final year &lt;strong&gt;dissertation with a strong head start&lt;/strong&gt; in terms of skills and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;poster.jpg&#34; align=&#34;right&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34;&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;I had the pleasure of joining the Reality Bending Lab (ReBeL) along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/authors/auz-moore/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Auz&lt;/a&gt;, as the first two members since the lab moved to the UK. The title of my project was &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Exploring the Correlation between Interoception and Primal World Beliefs&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, which involved collecting &lt;strong&gt;physiological data&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g., heart rate, respiration, &amp;hellip;) in various tasks, analysing them, and investigating the relationship between various measures. The project started from scratch, where I learned how to use the &lt;strong&gt;JavaScript package JsPsych&lt;/strong&gt; to build the entire paradigm via coding. I also received detailed training on how to run a lab-based experiment, something I used to be worried but am now &lt;strong&gt;extremely confident about&lt;/strong&gt;. After collecting the data from 20 participants (&lt;em&gt;summer time goes by veryyyy fast!&lt;/em&gt;), I learned how to make and visualize Bayesian correlations in R. The output of this project was made into an academic poster, where I had to be creative and selective, to be presented at the poster session (see below). Additionally, we created the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/RealityBending/SussexPhysioProtocol&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sussex Psychophysiological Research Protocol&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a document aiming at providing guidelines for the best practices in psychophysiological research, to benefit future research done at Sussex. It might not seem like much, but it felt like doing real contributions to research, which was great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something important I learned is, beyond pure academic excellence, research is also about community and networking. It was a great occasion to &lt;strong&gt;informally meet many researchers&lt;/strong&gt;, and make bonds with other students. What is cool is that the JRA journey doesn&amp;rsquo;t stop abruptly and continues into the next academic year, as all candidates are invited to present their work at the &lt;strong&gt;JRA conference&lt;/strong&gt; held by the university in October. This was an amazing opportunity to get a glimpse of what a scientific conference might be, feel proud about your work, connecting with fellow students, learning how to talk about research with other staff members, and gaining public speaking skills. For those who are more ambitious, why not submit your work to the national level, and present it in the British Conference for Undergraduate Research (BCUR)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, I see the JRA as a golden key to open countless possibilities for your &lt;strong&gt;future career path&lt;/strong&gt;. For those considering applying to &lt;strong&gt;postgraduate studies&lt;/strong&gt; or research assistants, the strong research experience you gained will &lt;strong&gt;put you at the top of the list&lt;/strong&gt;. Even for those who decided to not do research in the future, it will still be rewarding as it gives a clear idea of what career you do not want. Don&amp;rsquo;t miss on it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;- Jing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2024-03-12-jingjra/ceremony_hu6453224026432249977.webp 400w,
               /post/2024-03-12-jingjra/ceremony_hu13877427795351555558.webp 760w,
               /post/2024-03-12-jingjra/ceremony_hu7998517612034990612.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/post/2024-03-12-jingjra/ceremony_hu6453224026432249977.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
